It's important to realize that there is no one version of the mainframe, but rather
a series of computers that all adhere to the mainframe architecture.
By taking this course, you're learning all about the core fundamentals of the mainframe
architecture.
Like all other computers, the mainframe has memory, and you've probably seen memory
models before.
They're in laptops, phones, and the mainframe.
Applications and operating systems need memory, but there's only so much real physical
memory to go around.
Even on a fully loaded system, applications are always hungry for more, and sometimes
it makes sense to move some of that data from real memory out to auxiliary storage, sometimes
called virtual memory.
Of course, if that data is needed for fast or access later on, it can be moved back
into real memory.
On the mainframe, auxiliary or just aux storage is kept on direct access storage devices,
also known as Dazzdy.
These are full of hard drives, which can be either disk or solid state.
No matter how fast the drives are, they're still nowhere near as fast as real memory.
So the mainframe has to make a decision about where that data should be kept.
However, part of the mainframe architecture is based on this tight relationship between
real memory and aux storage.
It's for that reason that memory on the mainframe is usually just referred to as storage.
So when you hear storage, just know that we're talking about something that includes
both on-chip memory and aux storage.
Because the way the architecture works to the application running, it's all just storage.
So when an application comes along and says it needs a whole bunch of memory, all these components
work together so the application can carry on, like it has this nearly unlimited amount
of memory, when in fact all the complexities are being handled behind the scenes.
In ZOS, the mainframe operating system, we're going to be spending most of our time
talking about here.
Users and applications have access to their own individual address space.
An address space is simply a map of storage that is made available to users and applications.
The range of the address space goes all the way up to 16 exabytes.
And an exabyte is a unit that comes after petabytes.
So that's a lot of space.
And by giving an application an address space, it's basically saying, yes,
store your data anywhere you'd like in here, I'll manage it all for you.
And once it's up and running, ZOS will periodically check on that memory to see if some
of it can actually be migrated.
In ZOS, memory is placed into four kilobyte chunks called pages.
When that memory is in central storage on real memory, it occupies what's called a frame.
And when it's moved out to aux storage, it takes up a slot.
When the OS decides to move a slot to a frame or a frame to a slot, that's called paging.
And we like for paging to happen as little as possible on the mainframe.
Hopefully the OS identifies the right frames to page out the slots.
And they don't have to be page back in because that paging back and forth is a fairly
complex procedure.
All of these changes are kept track of in a series of tables maintained by the operating
system.
In a well-tuned system with adequate real storage, memory gets paged out once and most
of it stays there.
The concept of virtual memory is certainly not unique to the mainframe.
But the way in which it handles its virtual memory, you can see it's something pretty special.
The most current generation of the mainframe architecture is known as the Z architecture.
And it includes not only the hardware found in the mainframe, but the mainframe operating
systems, which are built to take advantage of the hardware's features.